All right. So now um it's my pleasure to
um welcome our speaker for today, Albert
Gu. Um he's an assistant professor in
the machine learning department at
Carnegie Mellon University and the chief
scientist of Cartesia AI.
And his research broadly focuses on
theoretical and empirical foundations of
deep learning.
And he's a particularly known for new
approaches to deep sequence modeling and
neural network architectures
and was recognized on the Time AI 100
list of most influential researchers in
2024. And previously he completed his
PhD here at Stanford. So without further
ado, let's welcome Albert.
>> [applause]
>> All right. Thank you, Stephen. Um
Does this work? Okay. Um so I'll just
get started. It's good to be back. I
think I haven't been back on campus in a
while even though it's only been like 2
years since I graduated.
Um
So this talk just as a disclaimer, um so
the talk is called on the tradeoffs of
state space models and transformers. Um
I've given versions of this talk over
the last
year or so
um and I turned it into a blog post as
well. So if you've seen those, they
might not be uh this talk won't be too
different. There is a little bit of new
content. Um
uh but don't expect anything that new.
Um and afterwards uh the blog post would
also be a good supplement to this as
well if you want to take a look at it.
Um
So in the last two or three years
there's been a big surge in popularity
of alternative architectures to
transformers. Um
particularly models that are so-called
sub-quadratic or linear in complexity.
Um some examples of these include the uh
original Mamba model um which came out
just over 2 years ago um and arguably
popularized a lot of the subsequent line
of work. Um there have now been
follow-ups to Mamba, Mamba 2, and just a
month ago we published Mamba 3. Um so
there's continually progress being made
here. Um other models you may have heard
of include xLSTM
um which is a refinement of the original
LSTM which is um in some in some ways
kind of the original most popular RNN um
that was the canonical sequence model
used before transformers.
Um
Other models that are popular are uh
DeltaNet and the follow-up gated
DeltaNet which combines DeltaNet with
Mamba 2.
Um this is another very popular model
that's been um is now pretty widely
used. Um and also another paradigm
called test time training which um views
recurrence as a form of test time
updates that optimize an optimization
function. Um so these are a couple
umbrella families of models
um that are all quite popular now. And
um we're seeing them used more and more
in actual large-scale um kind of
production quality models. Um after
Mamba came out it became used in a bunch
of hybrid models um that combine these
linear layers with attention layers
um including Jamba from AI21, um Zamba
from Zyfra, and Samba from Microsoft. Um
more recently there are models that
include um
uh Hunyuan from uh Tencent which was
uh actually like several hundred billion
parameters. Um the latest Qwen models
um are now based on gated DeltaNet. Um
Kimmy Linear is another uh hybrid model
that's based on some um
uh follow-up gated DeltaNet.
Um I think very recently uh AI2
uh also released a new Olmo model that
is hybrid and it also uses gated
DeltaNet combined with attention. Um and
somewhere here I forgot to list uh the
NeMo-Megatron models from Nvidia um are
also very new. I think the latest one is
the NeMo-Megatron 3 models
um which have been scaled to again
hundreds of billions of parameters
um
and that model uses Mamba 2. So again,
these models are actually um very very
widely used now. Um
And so
uh today I'm going to be talking about a
lot of these models and uh rather than
focusing on any particular one, I'm
going to kind of zoom out and talk about
general characteristics of these models,
how do I think about them,
um how do I think about transformers,
and how these models relate to each
other.
Um
There's uh these models are there's a
lot of different, you know, models here
um like these and many many more. Um and
there's a lot of names used to refer to
them. So in this talk I'm going to call
them state space models which is um what
uh Mamba was considered to be. Um
But there are actually many different
lineages of work that have appeared kind
of in parallel.
Um and there are other names for like
related models that um
for the most part, at least for the
purposes of this talk, are largely
interchangeable. So other things that
you can call these include um linear
attention.
Um They're all kind of recurrent models,
so you can call them kind of like just
recurrent models. I sometimes call them
modern recurrent models as opposed to
kind of the older ones like the LSTM.
Um you can call them
um linear RNNs
um or just broadly linear models, right?
So um usually these days when people say
any of these words, it kind of broadly
refers to uh really any of these models.
Um
And uh when we say hybrid models, we
mean kind of one of these combined with
quadratic attention.
Okay. So
um these again are actually generic
architectures and they can be used
pretty much anywhere.
Uh but for the most part in this talk we
will also focus on autoregressive
modeling. So um this is something you're
probably all familiar with. Um
paradigm um such as
um for language models where
uh you have a model that uh models next
token probabilities um of a sequence and
then um it can act as a generative model
where you can sample from the model by
um repeatedly sampling a token and
feeding it back to the model.
Um the reason we focus on this is uh for
two reasons. First of all, it's in some
sense the most important modeling
paradigm right now, especially for
language modeling.
Um and secondly, for all for
understanding the tradeoffs of these um
different sequence models, it's actually
helpful to think about autoregressive
modeling.
Um and so just to put us on the same
page, um
we'll really quickly go over what does
uh inference or sampling look like for
these models.
Um so I'm not going to, you know,
redefine attention everything. Um
But uh from kind of a a zoomed out point
of view, what attention does at
inference time is that um you give it a
prompt which is, you know, a set of
tokens. Um
And then the model tries to predict the
next um token or uh word um by doing
these pairwise comparisons against every
single previous token that it's seen,
right? So um
you do these comparisons, um you run
some calculations, and then you can uh
predict the next word. Um and then you
can put this back into your prompt and
then repeat this, right? So um what
characterizes attention is this ability
to look over every single past uh token
that you've seen in the context.
Um
So um this, like even without defining
exactly what attention is, this I think
is a very useful characterization of it.
Um because I kind of think of
transformers as the canonical model that
caches every past token
um because it needs to cache every token
in order to do these sort of
comparisons.
Um to get a little bit more specific,
this is called the KV cache which I
think everyone probably knows. Um a lot
of the work around transformers
basically has to deal with the KV cache,
right? Ways of compressing it um and so
on and so forth. Um this and again, like
uh it doesn't actually matter that it's
called the KV cache. That's an artifact
of the way transformers are defined, but
you know, at any higher level basically
transformer is just a model that stores
this cache.
Um and because it stores this cache,
this really defines its computational
characteristics.
Um in particular, uh it's heavily
dependent on the size of its context and
the memory and computation scales with
the context.
Um Now if you amortize this over
inference um then uh instead of scaling
linearly with the context, the model
scales quadratically in compute. And so
this is why um attention is considered a
quadratic model.
Um and at a high level um what again
what attention does is it does all these
comparisons. Um and what state space
models do is that um
again, in inference time as your tokens
stream in um instead of storing all of
them explicitly, the model um squishes
them all into a state basically uh
represented by this blue ball here. And
then the individual tokens are kind of
thrown away and the model only interacts
with data through the state.
Um and then it it does this repeatedly
online, right? So you can generate new
token and put it back into your state.
Um the state is highly compressed which
means that every single step of
inference time takes constant time and
then uh summing this over a sequence
takes linear time. So this is why we
call them linear models.
And so um this is really just kind of a
high-level way to think about it and it
it these are the ways that really
distinguish these families of models.
Um so now let me talk a little bit about
the actual uh definition of these models
and what I think are kind of the most
important ingredients that go in.
Um so first of all, the
um state space models are basically
defined by this equation down here.
Um So it is essentially a
um a special type of recurrence
with a few key characteristics.
Um we think of this recurrence as a
sequence mapping from
uh an input X
Um
And when you unbind this along the
sequence length, uh you can think of X
as basically a one-dimensional number or
a scalar.
Um
It gets blown up with a vector B
um and then summed into some uh
transformation of a hidden state. So uh
every step, just like a normal
recurrence, you update the hidden state
and then you incorporate the input. And
then there's this recurrent hidden state
um denoted by H that kind of
characterizes recurrent models.
Right? Um some differences between SSMs
and some of the older RNNs are that
um
first of all, this uh this recurrence is
linear.
Um there's no non-linearity that's
applied um after this equation like they
are in
um GRUs, LSTMs, and some of the older
RNNs.
Second of all,
some of the big differences include
these ingredients. So, the first kind of
main one that differs a lot from past
traditional RNNs is that the state size
is much larger. So, the way I define
this is that X here is a one-dimensional
input and the hidden state and for a
one-dimensional input the hidden state
becomes n-dimensional where n is usually
on the order of
it's like 64 or 128 or so, so kind of
the state is 100 times bigger than the
input.
And so, this is very different than how
LSTMs were defined.
The reason this is important is because
your
auto aggressive state here is a
bottleneck of your context, right?
Because all the context got compressed
into the state. So, the larger your
state is, the more information your
model can remember, which is really
important on information dense
modalities such as for language
modeling.
The second key ingredient is that not
only does the state have to be large,
but it has to be expressive enough to
remember exactly what the model wants to
remember. So, abstractly you can think
of any RNN as a function that
combines the previous hidden state with
a new input. And so, you have a black
box function and different
parameterizations of the function define
different RNNs.
And making this more expressive
allows the model to be more precise
about the information it's modeling.
Um
So, one
key difference with some of the later
SSMs such as Mamba
compared to old older models is that
the parameters here are defined to be
functions of the input itself.
And this is again different not only
from older SSMs, but also, you know,
again different from LSTMs. We call this
activity because it means that the model
by having its own parameters be
functions of the input, the model can
control based on the input how to
control the recurrence, which lets the
model be more precise in selecting what
information to remember.
Because, for example, if A here is a
function of the input and I don't want
to remember the input, then I can set A
to be I can look at the input and then
decide that I want A to be zero. Or
sorry, I want A to be like one and B to
be zero.
Or if I really want to remember the
input, maybe throw away the previous
context, I can set A to be zero. Right,
so this activity makes the state update
function much more expressive and this
was really a key ingredient in getting
these models to be effective.
The final ingredient is that
both the first two ingredients, the
state size and the more expressive state
update function,
make the model much more expressive and
um
have much more capacity, but also makes
the model much harder to compute. And
so, in particular, unlike a traditional
RNN,
it's actually basically impossible to
compute this by computing the
recurrence. And so, a lot of the work
involved in this family of models
was
to find clever ways of rewriting the
computation to compute the training pass
of this much, much faster.
The original
Some ideas here include associative
scan, which is what the original Mamba
model used.
Basically, by exploiting the fact that
this recurrence is linear, you can
parallelize the computation using a
specific algorithm.
And later versions of this, including
Mamba 2 and including many of the other
variants like the gated DeltaNet,
completely rewrite this in terms of this
chunked matrix multiplication.
So, really
I think these are kind of the three most
important ingredients. There's a lot
more details that are involved in how
exactly do parameterize all of these,
how to initialize all of these, and so
on.
But I think these are kind of the the
main reasons that made these models
effective.
And all of these ingredients actually
existed prior to this recent line of
work. For example, linear attention
first was published I think in 2020 and
it basically used something similar to
this that had this state size expansion.
Classical RNNs can be viewed as some
form of selectivity or gating. Um
And many models have already used these
ideas for
more efficient computation including
these older linear RNNs.
So, none of these ingredients All these
ingredients were used before,
but Mamba kind of can be viewed as the
first model that actually combined all
three of these and that was critical for
it to be actually really effective. And
it was perhaps the first model that
demonstrated that recurrent models can
actually be competitive with
transformers
on information dense
modalities like language.
Um
We now know that this statement has a
bit of a caveat.
There is much more nuance to, you know,
modeling than just perplexity, for
example, but this certainly showed that
from, you know, a course grain
perspective like perplexity,
these completely different architectures
could actually be competitive.
Since then, there's been again a lot of
work. This is a nice table from the
DeltaNet paper,
but since then there's been even more
models.
But basically, there's a lot of
different variations of these models
that
are really effective, but I think all of
them are kind of
pretty similar to each other. They're
all variants that all include these
three ingredients and tweak different
definitions of them. So, many of these
vary the state update a little bit. Some
of them change the computation a little
bit, but all care a lot about
efficiency.
And to give kind of a
an like a, you know, off the record kind
of a
what I think are the most effective
ones,
probably right now the most
tried and true variants of these are
Mamba 2 and gated DeltaNet. Those are
also the ones that are most popularly
used in large scale hybrid models.
Gated DeltaNet is
a little more powerful, but a little
slower version of Mamba 2. So, depending
on your needs,
both of these are pretty good, but
depends on what exactly you want. Mamba
3 just came out and it's a little bit
less tested at scale, but also will
probably be up there.
But more importantly, all of these
models I think are actually much more
similar to each other than they are to
attention. And it's more important to
instead of talking about the exact
details between all of these,
I think it's more interesting to think
about the higher level trade-offs
between these and attention.
So, that's what the rest of the talk
will be about.
Um
So again, we're going to examine this
through the nature of auto aggressive
modeling. And one of the key points here
is that I claim that the trade-offs of
sequence models can be understood
through examining their auto aggressive
state.
What is the auto aggressive state?
So,
in some sense every auto aggressive
model can be viewed as carrying an
implicit state, right? So, um
This can literally be defined as if
you're examining an auto aggressive
model during generation time like in
this animation,
the state is what the model stores in
memory in between each step of
generation.
So, for a SSM, the state is just going
to be its fixed size kind of a matrix
valued state.
For attention, the state is going to be
its KV cache.
Um
And the definitions of these states
really inform the
the trade-offs of these models and their
inductive biases.
So, we previously said that again, we
kind of talked about how these models
generate. So, transformers are
quadratic
by looking at every single past token.
And SSMs are linear time because they
compress everything into a state. Um
A simple analogy that I like is that I
think of transformers like a database.
So, if you think about the nature of its
state, which is the KV cache, what it's
doing is it's storing a representation
of every single token or every single
element of the sequence it's seen
before. Right, and it's basically
writing it down to its database and as
the sequence length grows, it's kind of
expanding its database.
And it's able to attend or look back
very precisely onto
any element of this database.
On the other hand, SSMs are more like a
brain in that it is a
fixed size method and again, it kind of
compresses all the information it's seen
into this fixed size state. So, this
has completely different characteristics
than a database.
And many of the trade-offs of these
models can be kind of intuited from this
analogy. So, for example, um
some of the weaknesses of SSMs are that
they are not so good at retrieval. And
this is exactly the way that brains work
as well. Humans are notoriously bad at
remembering exact strings of numbers or
and so on.
But also comes with advantages. Um
But yeah, so at first pass the talking
about the trade-offs of SSMs, um
they're kind of the canonical stateful
and compressive model.
Statefulness is really powerful because
it's what allows these models to be
really efficient in online settings. Um
Kind of again, just like brains are,
it's always online, always able to
consume information at a constant rate
and interact with the world in real
time.
These are places that these sort of
linear models are likely to be very good
at.
Um
The compressiveness of it also has
subtle benefits, which I'll talk about
later in the talk.
And the downsides are that because of
the fixed size state, these lack
fine-grained recall and retrieval
abilities. So, there's many kind of
synthetic tasks like, you know, the
haystack, associative recall, these sort
of things that involve
asking a query and digging out precise
bit of information from your context.
These models are not so good at it just
like brains are.
Um
Now again, the analogy has more
implications because, for example, if
you think about human intelligence, it's
actually not just the brain. Humans use
a lot of external tools
um assist and that this really augments
our ability
um to process and it kind of um
it's uh it augments intelligence. Right?
So, if you think of um human-like
intelligence really as the combination
of um our processing unit um as well as
external scratch pads, um then
um this actually this analogy also
predicts the behavior of models. And so,
this is kind of one um high-level
inspiration for hybrid models.
um
Starting from the advent of these uh
state-space models, they've been used in
hybrid models for this reason. um
There's a few references here that refer
to uh some of the older ones. um but
again, I uh there's now many, many more
versions of these. Um some of which are
are very, very large scale.
um And one thing that's been pretty
remarkable
is that um when uh many different groups
independently kind of verified the uh
optimal ratios of hybrid models.
Um so, the simplest way to define a
hybrid is just to interleave your um
your linear layer with your quadratic
attention layer. Right? And then the
question is what ratio of these layers
should you include?
um
Many of these older papers found
something remarkably um consistent that
it's something close to a 10:1 ratio of
SSM layers to attention layers seemed
optimal
um at least from a perplexity
standpoint. um Nowadays, um this ratio
seems have changed a little bit as
uh models are getting better. um But I
think that it's still very consistent
that uh people typically use something
like at minimum a 3:1 or 4:1 ratio of
linear layers to quadratic layers.
um
And so, what's interesting about this is
that if you use the analogy and you
think about human intelligence, um you
might also kind of predict this because
um we tend to think of the the brain as
the main processing unit and the
external databases, scratch pads, and so
on as a supplement um that you know,
helps you store information, but is not
actually the main um computational
lifter. Right? And so, um the fact that
when you actually do these very careful
ablations and find that you want more
linear layers than quadratic, and this
is not accounting for computation. It's
just what makes the best performance. um
It's pretty interesting that kind of
follows the analogy as well.
um And so, um
kind of a thought is that
while um these linear models are
sometimes viewed as having a critical
drawback because the finite state means
you can't remember everything, it seems
like this compression is a weakness. um
It's actually not so clear because even
if we're just looking at performance
without um looking at speed, um you
actually do want a lot of linear layers
here. And so, I think a a general theme
is about um
is the compression actually
fundamentally important to intelligence
and um what role does it play there? Uh
and once again, um there will be a very
interesting experiment experiment I'll
show later that hopefully touches on
this again.
Okay. So, now we're going to switch and
talk about um
just transformers. So,
um although, you know, there's a lot of
work here on transformer alternatives,
um transformers are still kind of the
to-go model
um for many things, especially language,
and for good reason. They're very, very
powerful.
um
And there's kind of a prevailing um
uh mindset that uh they basically work
on everything and um you know, they've
they're really used in pretty much all
fields um from language to vision to
many more.
um And many many people think that you
basically should just um
use a transformer
um and uh just put your data into it and
it kind of just works.
um And this is kind of true, actually.
um But there are nuances to it. So,
um the way I think about it is that
attention is actually most effective um
when your data is at the right level of
abstraction.
um What this means is that in any
pipeline you actually see where trans-
transformers are used,
um there are pretty substantial
encoder-decoder layers that transform
the data to a form that is suitable for
a transformer to process.
um So, to give some examples, um when
you use these models in
uh vision domains,
um for example,
uh this figure is from the I think the
original uh vision transformer paper uh
for classification. um What they do is
they take your image and divide it into
these patches, which are basically uh
vision tokens,
um and then uh encode it a little bit
and then pass into the transformer.
Right? And then um and so, basically
it's kind of making your data much
coarser and in a form uh
uh that's more suitable for the
transformer. um And I claim that this
sort of encoding step is actually
critical for the transformer to work
well.
um In language, this encoder is called
the tokenizer. So, um
you know, if you have a string of um
characters like if you're modeling
English, you know, technically you could
have just put this into your model and
it should work. um
And um but we actually process it using
a tokenization step that splits it into
these uh coarser chunks.
um
And many people actually don't really
think about this step. We kind of always
just use off-the-shelf tokenization. um
But again, I claim that this step is
actually really critical for
transformers to work, not just for
efficiency reasons, but actually from
kind of a modeling perspective in terms
of what the what sort of um features and
transformations the transformer can
capture.
um
So, tokenization is notorious because it
has a lot of problems. um So, we can ask
what happens if you don't tokenize. um
There's a there's a number of outspoken
critics against tokenization. This is a
tweet taken from Andrej Karpathy um
where he kind of enumerates a bunch of
edge cases with tokenization. um
It causes issue, you know, in spelling,
in um
it has many sort of edge cases. um
Uh if you ever kind of prompt your model
with out uh ending it in a space, um
or maybe it's
ending it in a space.
Uh one of these two will, you know,
screw up your model. So, you have to be
very deliberate and these are all edge
cases in tokenization.
um
However, you know, most of these edge
cases are understood and most people uh
you can engineer away a lot of these
with good data or with other tricks.
um And so, many people think that this
is not a real problem.
um But if you could solve tokenization
uh if you can get rid of it, you know,
you would solve these for free. um And I
think that even um
even if the engineering solution kind of
just works, it's still a worthwhile
problem to address uh for philosophical
reasons.
Because um AI has always been about
learning um automatically from raw data
and models that are more and more
end-to-end generally tend to be better.
um This also reflects on the bitter
lesson.
um If you can find models that are more
generic and work without with less
feature engineering,
um but benefit more from scale, you'll
eventually get better models that learn
better features from data.
um So, what happens if you actually
train models without tokenization? So,
um one simple thing you can do is just
look at language modeling, but um not
tokenize your data before. So, basically
you can uh just pass in raw characters
into your model.
um So, this is a plot from uh a recent
paper of ours, um but it was first done
by this paper called Mamba Byte, which
basically just tried to compare uh Mamba
against transformers on byte-level
modeling.
um So, again, here you basically just uh
don't use your BPE tokenizer on the
data. um And these are some training
curves
um for models that are uh matched in
size and just uh
uh trained for longer.
um So, what you see here is that
um
the uh SSM here is actually uh much,
much better than the transformer. So,
the purple line here is a uh sliding
window attention model.
um And the blue line is um just the
Mamba model and these are kind of
isotropic models that are
um basically equivalent in every way.
um And there's a you can see there's
like a very, very large gap here. um If
you kind of draw the horizontal line to
see
um the data efficiency difference,
it's like basically like 2x or
something.
um And even if you let the attention be
global, and in this case because byte
sequences are so long, this is really
increasing the computation,
um so that the global attention model in
a dashed the dashed line here um is
doing 2x as much compute as the Mamba
model, um it's actually still not as
good.
um
And so, what this means is that um
there's a there's actually a fundamental
difference here. And it's not just
because of that attention is slower.
Because the one that is um the
comparison between these two bottom
lines are kind of the same model size,
same data, same sequence length, um and
it's simply letting the attention do
its, you know, quadratic thing and using
much more compute, but it's still a bit
worse.
Okay.
So, um this phenomenon occurs in other
settings, too. So, um we can look at
kind of sequence-like data that is not
just language or kind of language uh
with alternative vocabularies. um
This is a figure from the original Mamba
paper that uh we investigated the model
on DNA modeling. So, again, you can
basically just take DNA sequences and do
autoregressive modeling on them.
um
And here the comparison between the the
uh orange and the red line is the Mamba
versus transformer, um where
uh once again, we see that there's
actually a really big gap. And if you
kind of um
try to match for computer match for
parameters, the Mamba model is about 3x
more efficient.
um
So, these are
settings that basically don't have
tokenization. um And so, what is going
on here?
um So, when I think about what attention
is good at, there's a couple of
heuristics that I think are really
helpful um for for thinking about um
the types of like what it does and the
types of settings that it excels at. um
So, first of all, once again, thinking
about the
um autoregressive state. So, we kind of
thought of of the attention as storing a
database of every token it's seen.
Um, that means that
it
it should make sense to like actually
cache every single token, right? Um, and
in many in many you can think of like
many types of data where it actually
doesn't make sense to cache every token.
Um, obvious examples include like uh if
your data's noisy and there's um you
know spurious tokens that you don't need
or you know you can think of perhaps um
in the language setting um you know you
can often when we read English we can
often identify words uh even if you drop
out a lot of the tokens, right? Um, and
that's kind of a just a very coarse
analogy that shows that um you don't
need to spend all of the memory all that
computation to cache a representation of
every token because not every token is
meaningful.
Um, another heuristic is that um in some
ways
um softmax attention was developed as a
alternative to hard attention. What hard
attention means is that um with softmax
attention basically you take a weighted
combination of every token in your
context. Um, hard attention means that
imagine you can only take um you can
only look at a single token at a time.
Um
so this is also I think a useful proxy
for what attention does.
And um and once again it's helpful to
think about this
um
because um attention excels at data
where um hard attention makes sense.
Um, and so this is why again um use
applying attention to say character
level data
um
is much less effective because um
if you if you're going to think about
the nature of the data and how we
process it um you're never going to look
at a single character, right? You're
kind of paying attention to the data at
the semantic level of words or even
coarser.
Um, not at the level of characters. Um,
and this is this kind of is a very uh
heuristic explanation for the phenomenon
that we just saw.
Um, and so
if we kind of look at the different
types of data that you can use um
this this really I think is useful for
thinking about uh where attention is
useful. So if you have things like words
or subwords which is what we typically
apply apply transformers on um they
really excel because these sort of
tokens are intrinsically semantically
meaningful. Um, they're modular and
composable. It makes sense to want to
you know look at a single word
um or store a representation of a word.
When we start looking at other settings
they make less sense.
Um, if we're uh modeling characters or
like DNA base pairs
um every individual character basically
doesn't have any meaning every
individual uh you know DNA um base
doesn't have any meaning and so uh this
is one explanation for why attention
does so much worse here than other
models.
Um, and many other settings are not so
clean.
Um, for example in vision if you look at
a patch of an image um it's not really
clear which category they fall into.
Some of the patches may uh have a lot of
information uh some of them may have
very little like you might might just
get a patch of sky that's kind of
useless to your model. And so um the
tradeoffs there are a little bit less
clear. Um
but it goes to show why um when we move
away from kind of pure tokenized
language um actually these alternative
models um become more and more popular.
Um
and I think it's because of basically
this reason that um when you don't have
very well-defined tokenizers um the
power of transformers goes down and the
power of models that are doing this
implicit compression which in some ways
can be viewed maybe as sharing a similar
roles to organization um these models
get better. Um, so this is a graph taken
from um pretty soon after the moment
paper came out about where it was uh
most popularly used
um in applications.
And uh even though the model was kind of
um
pitched as a uh language model
um actually language only took up about
uh 10% of the applications. And instead
it's it was viewed as just a generally
useful sequence model for all sorts of
modalities from um time series to audio
to uh especially vision.
Um, all right so now
uh while we're on the topic of
tokenizers um
a very recent application of these
models has been again in the domain of
tokenizer free models.
Um, so very recently um
my group uh published a paper called
HNet which um
is maybe the latest model that tries to
do actual tokenizer free um modeling of
language.
Um
so in a nutshell um
the way I'll describe HNet is that it's
a end-to-end hierarchical network and
that's what HNet stands for hierarchical
network.
Um
uh that operates on raw data and
compresses it through a data dependent
chunking process.
Um
so I'll unpack this in a little bit um
but basically you think of this as a
model that is uh operating on raw data
and implicitly trying to tokenize it by
chunking it inside the model.
Um, this work was largely led by my
student um Sukjun Hwang here. Um, and
this is the name of the paper.
Um
but kind of the this is a really general
net uh neural network architecture
that's um
really about the idea of compression.
Um, where it's most obviously useful is
simply on tokenizer free language
modeling. Um, so to contrast
um
again the way that all of our our
language models work is through an
explicit tokenization step. Um, if
you're familiar with this
um the most common one is called BPE or
byte pair encoding and it's basically
some form of heuristics that uh take
your sentence of low-level data like
characters and then um
implements some uh some merge rules that
uh group them together into bigger
chunks, right? So for example this
sentence might be tokenized exactly like
this.
Um, where uh characters got merged
together into these um
I'm calling them chunks but uh we
usually call them tokens.
Um, what the HNet does is that it will
um instead of doing this as a separate
offline step and then passing these into
the model um the HNet only sees the
original um
uh characters. So for example the vocab
size would be just say like 256 if
you're working on bytes.
Um, and then the model is implicitly
it's looking for boundaries like this
but this is all happening inside the
model. Um, and this is a visualization
of what the model actually might do
during training.
Um, so this this depicts the training
stage of the model.
Um
I think the animation started partway
through for some reason. Um, but
basically the model is modeling just
bytes um and the green denotes where the
model is trying to put boundaries.
Um, and so this is at the like at the
beginning of training the model is um
doing a lot of exploring cuz it doesn't
know how.
Um, and then it eventually kind of
stabilizes on boundaries that are quite
aligned with where we would expect um a
good tokenizer to do. Um, in particular
on English it happens to coincide that
um
your tokens generally want to be where
spaces are but if you look closely um
you you can see that the model is like
here for example okay the animation
started but you can see that the model
is actually finding semantically
meaningful subwords as well and um if
you compose this you'll find that the
model finds semantically meaningful
groups of words.
Um
so uh this was a major step towards
actually doing um tokenizer free
modeling uh without you know the
separate offline step.
Um, so
um I won't go
fully into the details cuz the model's
pretty complicated but uh try to give a
high level of how this works.
Um
so this here on the left depicts the um
kind of the the uh general structure of
the model.
Um
and so we think of it as hierarchical
because there are um two main stages.
Um, there's parts of the model that
interface with uh kind of the
fine-grained data.
Um, so what happens is that the uh let's
say we're operating directly on bytes or
characters here.
Um, the sequence gets passed through
um a lightweight encoder which will just
be a generic um sequence model or
several layers of a sequence model.
Um, then there is a special routing
mechanism that um for every single
character predicts do I want this
character to be a boundary or not? Um,
or kind of like do I want it to be the
end of a chunk?
Um, then for the ones that are decided
to be chunks which are highlighted in
the colors here um we kind of summarize
each chunk and then and then um compress
them down into one representation. Uh
and so you can kind of think of the
encoder and the chunking as playing the
same role as the uh standard BPE
tokenizer.
Um
the uh okay and then then once that is
um compressed down then um you have a
much shorter sequence. Then you pass
this into what we call the main model
and this model you can just think of as
again a generic sequence model um that
is effective on chunks. And so here for
example um by default we will just use a
transformer because they're a tried and
true model that operate well on um words
or chunks or tokens.
Um
and so this is kind of the the inner
stage.
Um, then after your main model you take
your output representations and then you
expand them back out to the original
resolution um pass them through a
decoder and then um do your auto
aggressive prediction there. So at a
very coarse level it's it's really kind
of just um
it's kind of honestly similar to the
existing pipeline with a tokenizer and
then a transformer except the
tokenization happens inside the model
through an encoder and then a routing
mechanism to predict the boundaries.
Um
now uh yeah so there's a lot of details
here but uh the one thing I'll emphasize
for this talk is that um the outer
stages of this model which are the ones
that interface with the byte level data
um
strongly benefit from being SSMs. So um
just like the previous experiment I saw
where if you run these models on
character level data uh like an SSM
versus a transformer um the SSM is way
better. Um similarly here you'll find
that um any part of the model that
touches byte level data um
strongly benefits from being an SSM.
Um
and then there's outside of this there
is um there are a lot of details in the
exact chunking mechanism and um
other parts of the model that needed to
be optimized for this to work. So this
is this is a pretty non-trivial problem
um because this is kind of like a
discrete optimization problem that's
really unstable and difficult but um if
you get all right it actually works and
you actually can train a model that
operates fully on non-tokenized um
untokenized data. Um
and actually seems to scale pretty
reasonably and um
um can actually outperform your uh
standard tokenized pipeline.
Um
So these are uh some of the results that
we see.
Um on the left here is again uh training
plots where
uh we're fixing a model size and we're
just showing how the validation
perplexity or bits per byte uh decreases
as a function of the data seen.
Um and one thing to also emphasize is
that
um
sorry here in this diagram
the main stage I said can just be a
generic sequence model. That means that
the main stage itself can be another
H-Net. Um so that means that you can
basically compose this model to have
multiple stages of chunking. Right? And
so um what H-Net really means is that um
it's not it's not um per se about you
know uh tokenization-free modeling it is
about um dynamic chunking. So it's about
the idea of taking any data and
compressing it into uh larger chunks
that ideally represent more uh higher
level semantic meaning.
Uh and because it's done completely
end-to-end this is kind of the first
model that can not only chunk things but
also um chunk things multiple times to
get more and more levels of abstraction.
Um and what we see on the plot on the
right is that
the uh on the left is that the
transformer baseline here is in is the
black line.
Um
and then if you train a H-Net um with
just a single stage of chunking like uh
in the previous diagram
um it starts off worse than a
transformer but after seeing enough data
it crosses over and seems to be scaling
better.
Um
and the reason for this is that um it
takes because like basically um
feature engineering generally is a form
of inductive bias that can uh help your
model in data-constrained regimes but
usually benefits less from scaling.
Right? So this is the common theme that
we see in deep learning. This is the uh
bitter lesson. Um and so we see this
exactly in this plot. Um if you apply a
stage of chunking then um it takes some
amount of data before the model learns
how to create good chunks um like we saw
in the animation. Um but once it does it
should theoretically be able to create
better chunks than what your hard-coded
BPE algorithm gave you.
Um and then if you compose the model by
nesting it again and doing two stages of
chunking uh the model seems to scale
even better. Although um there are other
um challenges that occur in this case
because uh you'll have more parameters
um it's harder to train and so on. Um
but at least um
these plots kind of track what we'd
intuitively expect.
Um
And and you can actually also uh it's
not shown in this plot sorry but um you
could also ask yourself what happens if
you run the H-Net directly on BPE tokens
um and then it kind of the behavior kind
of um again tracks what you expect. So
compared to a uh H-Net on bytes BPE
gives you some free boost because uh
you're getting the chunk the model uh
based on this kind of like hard-coded
features. Um
but if you just added another stage of
chunking to the H-Net and operate on
bytes then the model learns better
features than your BPE tokens and
um this is what it looks like.
And so um if you look at these
comparisons especially these two circle
in the red boxes um the theme is that
um no matter what setting you're in
um if you train a model operating on BPE
tokens it works pretty good but if you
can manage to throw away the BPE and
learn these chunks um end-to-end then
your model will do even better.
Um
One variation of this that is
particularly interesting
is that
um so again so H-Net is just a generic
architecture it doesn't have to be
applied on bytes. Um this plot shows
what happens um if you apply it on the
BPE data.
Um and I think this one's really
interesting because
um it relates back to uh this
compression
um argument that I talked about earlier.
So what we did here is that um we
applied a single stage H-Net to BPE
tokens and we varied the architecture in
the encoder and decoder.
Um so this plot basically um if we just
look at this top line and bottom line
um this says that the
uh the encoder is only transformer
layers.
Um
Uh the purple line and the red line is
where the encoder and decoder are only
Mamba layers and in between you can kind
of vary any combinations of these.
Um and then what we see here is that um
if you only have pure transformer layers
in the encoder and decoder uh there is
the model is noticeably worse and as
soon as you start putting in Mamba
layers into the encoder and decoder
model gets much better.
Um
And so what what is really interesting
here is that um
previously we kind of said that you know
transformers are great when your data is
already compressed um
like BPE tokens
um and they're less good when your data
is not compressed. Um so on on
characters Mamba is much better than
transformers. But in this experiment we
are entirely operating over BPE tokens
even in the outer stages. Right? And so
one might expect um
that putting transformers in the outer
layers is completely fine maybe even
better because they're only seeing BPE
tokens.
Um this plot is showing that even when
you're um compute matching everything
it's better to put Mamba in the outer
stages. And so the the lesson here to me
is that
um
the benefit of these SSMs is not just
about the resolution of the data they're
seeing but also about this um implicit
inductive bias toward compression.
Um
So I guess if you if you kind of look at
the diagram here um the role of the
encoder layers is not just to interface
with the given resolution of data but
it's also passing these representations
into the chunking layer right which is
deciding how to chunk the data and so
you can imagine that the encoder layers
are playing some role of compression as
well.
Um because literally the goal of it is
to try to produce a like a a literal
compression of the data in in temporal
sense.
Um
And so even when the data comes not as
characters but as BPE it seems that
applying linear models
uh or you can call them compressive
models because again of the fixed size
state um it's very critical. And so this
is I think the
the best evidence I've seen so far that
um the finite size state of uh recurrent
models is again not just for efficiency
but actually has fundamentally different
inductive biases and perhaps in a
setting like this it's actually doing
something like um I think of the H-Net
the goal of it is to create better
abstractions. Right? Um that's the
that's the goal of chunking you want to
take your characters and chunk them into
abstractions like words you might want
to turn your words into phrases that
have meaning um and toward this goal of
creating abstractions that's
fundamentally related to compression and
somehow these models actually
empirically seem very important for
that.
Um a final result I'll show on this
topic is um again you can apply these to
different types of data. Um
This is again another very recent paper
that was just put on archive a month ago
um where um we tried applying uh a
couple of different established
architectures to DNA modeling again. Um
and once again DNA is interesting
because
um in language you know modeling
characters is a bit of an academic
exercise it's like a long-term direction
um because we do exist we do have
tokenizers and most people are like why
not just use the tokenizer? Um in DNA
it's actually really difficult to define
tokenizers at least in a semantically
meaningful way like you can for English.
Um
and we see even bigger gaps generally
for these kind of alternative models. Um
this plot here shows um
instead of just fixing a model and
running out the uh training curve this
is actually showing formal scaling laws.
So each point here is a different flop
budget and then um the model size to
uh data amount was swept.
Um and so yeah so these are kind of
standard um scaling laws um but for DNA.
Um and we found um you know remarkably
linear um trends here.
Um And uh what's interesting again is
that these trends actually are so
different from language that uh usually
in language these lines are kind of just
shifted and you get kind of a constant
uh magnitude of improvement but um when
it comes to DNA um
the H-Net uh is actually discovering
patterns that you can't really find with
um
uh off-the-shelf tokenizers
uh and the it's actually scaling
fundamentally better.
Okay. So um
hopefully all of these have kind of
painted a picture that um these model
the different types of models really are
doing um very different things they have
very different inductive biases. Um
and this goes back to my main thesis
that I claimed which is that um
you know transformers work really really
well but they're particularly effective
when the data has already been encoded
properly and you often need different
types of models when your data is not
encoded or it's very difficult to
encode.
Um and so I think the future of modeling
will require um not just transformers
but a lot of other ideas.
Um
So far you know most people have viewed
transformers as basically just like a
very powerful tool. We don't really look
at it or touch it and we kind of design
the whole pipeline around it instead
through a lot of feature engineering,
through the way we process the data and
so on. Um but hopefully I've kind of
conveyed that there really is a lot of
different alternatives out there.
There's really a lot of room for
improvement.
I personally believe that there's
actually still a lot of room for major
improvements in architecture design.
Um okay, so just to come back now to the
uh
title of the talk on the tradeoffs just
to summarize. Um
SSMs
are largely thought of as a
alternative model that is more efficient
than transformers
but potentially more weak.
So the just by the way they're defined,
they're obviously more efficient. Um but
it's often pointed out the specific
problems they have especially with
retrieval like abilities.
Um
But I actually think that the efficiency
is a bit of a red herring. Um these
models are not just more efficient but
they're actually doing different form of
modeling. So again, I think of them as
being a stateful and a compressive model
and and these lead to
very different types of benefits that
they have from things like state
tracking which I didn't talk about today
to
things like building abstractions which
we kind of saw through the HNet.
Um and both of these pros and cons are
two sides of the same coin which is the
way it's auto aggressive state is
defined
in terms of this brain like state.
Um similarly attention um the strengths
are that it gets the ability to pay
attention to very specific details in
its context.
It's exceptionally strong at recall and
retrieval which is where SSM struggle.
Um and usually people think of the
downside as the efficiency
the quadratic scaling of attention.
Um but once again, I think that the
efficiency is a bit of a red herring and
the way I think really think about
attention is that
the downside is that it is highly
dependent on the resolution and the
semantic meaning of the data. Um so this
is through the examples we saw when you
change the resolution even in language
modeling from BP tokens to bytes,
the performance of attention changes
dramatically. Um and another way to put
this is that attention is beholden to
the tokens it's given. Because of the
way it's kind of caching every single
token,
um
it means that it's very sensitive to the
the resolution of the tokens it's given,
right? And has no ability to change what
a token means to it.
And once again, these pros and cons are
both two sides of the same coin
which is the way that it's auto
aggressive state is defined through this
database like cache.
Um and so I think that the
efficiency
arguments for both of these models are
um again a little bit of a distraction
because
at the end of the day, we just want the
models to model the things we want and
the exact efficiency there actually kind
of
it's not the right thing to look at
because there may be tasks for example
where you really do need the quadratic
attention. There may be tasks you know
where you actually have to cache and
memorize every single thing in your
context and you can't get around that,
right? And then so there's no point
arguing that the quadratic scaling is
bad.
Um
Um and to give kind of a a final picture
here. So one way to think about
architecture design in general is that
there's kind of a a picture where we
think of models as this black box where
during training you give it compute, you
know, and data
and then um
and then you create intelligent model
that has you know, wide range of
capabilities on the other side. Um
and in this in this picture you
basically think of your model training
as a vehicle that converts compute or
flops
into intelligence or capabilities.
Um and what you want is to find kind of
the most efficient vehicle that does
this conversion.
Um
And so the the central question to ask
is simply is my model using every single
flop it's given
wisely.
Right? And so
um
again like there there are settings
where you actually need to spend a lot
of compute in order to do some
capabilities but there are also settings
where
your model is doing a lot of compute
that is that doesn't really make sense.
For example, if your transformer is
given character level data, it doesn't
need to be caching every single
character into its KB cache. Um and so
this is the central question of
architecture design is designing better
and better black boxes here that perform
this conversion
and I think there's still a lot of room
for improvement there.
Okay, that's the end of the talk.
Uh
questions.
>> [applause]
>> Okay, awesome. Thanks Albert for the
very insightful talk. We're going to be
soliciting some questions now.
We're going to be balancing between our
in-person questions and those online. Um
so we can get started with some
in-person questions if anybody here has
any.
Thank you. I really admire your work.
I'm a PhD in Chris Ray's lab as well and
we constantly looking through all your
old papers so I really appreciate it. Um
a lot of the
uh current SSM inspiration is
uh
you know, trying to trade off some
recurrent expressivity for trainability
under the condition of using backprop or
backprop through time which you
mentioned the brain a bunch of times.
There's very little evidence that we're
keeping C copies of the brain and doing
backprop through time. It'd be very
unrealistic that we're doing that. Um so
there it must exist some other solver
that is happening inside your brain
right now.
Um what are your thoughts on that?
Yeah, that's a great question. So um
I'm actually a big fan of some of these
works that try to look at completely
different computation paradigms. Um I
think a lot of what drives my work is
the idea that we are probably in some
sort of local optimum and in the entire
way that all of our training is set up.
Um from you know, the architecture which
is where a lot of this is focused
but also even to bigger things like you
know, backprop and so on.
It is also not clear to me that backprop
is the best thing to do. Um
And there's a lot of um
yeah, there's a lot of codependence
between the model design and just the
the physical hardware we have and the
realities of these things.
I personally haven't thought that much
about backprop myself but um I have
thought about like it could cause
serious issues with for example like
one like one issue is um it causes a
physical memory constraint on your long
range dependencies because if you're
using backprop, then if you can't fit
your entire sequence in memory, you
literally can't learn dependencies. Um
you can you know, you can cook up
pathological examples where you just
literally can never learn dependencies
that are long enough.
So it could be a problem.
It could be the case that for any
realistic task that we care about, we
can engineer it to be good enough which
is kind of the way the world is going.
Um
But I do think that there are probably
other kind of
um you know, like getting out of the
local optimum and doing much more much
bigger changes these models. Another
example is that
as I mentioned, a lot of the work that's
been done here is on making these models
efficient on current hardware like GPUs.
Um you actually sacrifice a bunch of
expressivity that you could gain back by
adding true recurrence and there has
been like another line of work on trying
to do this but it really struggles
because it's just so hard to compute.
I actually think that that's another
line of work that's quite promising and
I have some um my own ideas there
but I think that you actually again like
you might be able to get fundamentally
better models by completely reimagining
you know, the the constraints that we
currently have.
Great. Any other in-person questions?
Thanks for the amazing talk.
Yeah, it's really interesting to see
your results with HNet and the dynamic
chunking mechanism and yeah, it's really
cool that it sort of gets better
performance on on DNA sequence modeling
and stuff. I was curious if you feel the
chunking mechanism is sort of elegant
and like will play a substantial role in
future models.
Yeah, so it's hard to say. So we worked
on this which took a long time because I
did fundamentally fundamentally believe
that chunking is
a really critical primitive that will
lead to better models in the long term.
Um
The
version that we published is you know,
just the first step there. I think it
was it was the first really end-to-end
model that works.
I don't think that is the end game at
all. Um there are improvements that you
can probably make to all parts of it
including the chunking mechanism itself.
Um
And I think so far it's not really been
validated at larger scales but um
yeah, but I think I think it's just you
know, the way I think about it is that
philosophically even, it just feels like
it's so important to learn these things
from scratch that I do think that coming
up with better and better chunking
mechanisms could be really important for
future models.
Uh
Thank you. Uh so just one technical
question. I'm curious like since you're
setting the separators at arbitrary
points like typically with a tokenizer,
you have a set dictionary. So, like I'm
curious how you feed that sequence in
when
the, you know, the sequence chunks can
vary very dynamically.
Um
but I'm
I guess more generally, you've drawn
several comparisons to like
how the human brain works. This is
something I'm also interested in.
Like
this aspect of are we doing some sort of
dynamic
like analysis of incoming data? What
What data do we need to remember
or compress or curate? Uh I've been
interested in that
towards like
improving the amount of memory that
models have access to. So, I'm curious
what your perspective would be on like
using these types of state-based models
perhaps to
curate
memories or curate more efficient memory
for like an attention-based or a lookup
based model to use down the line to
extends the amount that we're able to
actually memorize
uh in a like a continuous interaction.
Um all right. So, two questions there.
So, first I think the first one was
about a little more mechanically um
uh how the model works. So, um this is
actually one key advantage of the model
is So, I think the question is about
um
normally, when you use BPE, you have
kind of a fixed vocabulary and you'll
each vocabulary, you know, you'll look
up an embedding that pass to your model.
Um one of the challenges of tokenized
free models is that if you have an
infinite size vocabulary, you can't
have, you know, infinite embeddings. And
so, that's um that's So, what what
happens here is that um we don't need to
think about those embeddings at all
because
um because everything is happening
inside the model end-to-end, there is no
lookup table at all once you get past
the the very first encoding stage. So,
here you think of this model as just
operating on a vocabulary of whatever
fine-grained units you have, which might
be, you know, a size of 256 if it's a
byte.
Uh you get like embeddings here, then
you pass this into your model, and at
every future stage, you're just working
in embedding space.
Um and what's So, for example, the way
you create this embedding,
um the simplest way is just So, let's
say this embedding corresponds to this
chunk here.
Um the simplest way is just to literally
just copy and paste like whatever this
uh embedding is on the other side just
gets passed through, and we
uh ignore all the ones in between. Or
you can kind of just pull over each this
uh this chunk here.
Um so, basically, at the end of the
encoder stage, you have embeddings in
some latent space. And then you decide
where you want the chunks to be in and
your embedding that gets passed into the
main stage is just, say, pulling over
that chunk.
Um the second question is about, I
think, the um analogy to brains and so
on. Um to be clear, these analogies are
very very coarse. Um I think I, you
know, I'm not a neuroscientist. Um they
might yell at me if they heard these
analogies. Um but I think like a lot of
this is just kind of inspiration as I
use humans more as a proof of concept of
like what um things should be possible
with intelligence and what are some
really high-level ways that these might
be achievable.
Um
I
I mean, I will say that like chunking, I
think, is a concept that was directly
inspired by um
cognitive psychology. Um
but I think that it actually one of the
things I do think it will be useful for
is kind of
as a more clever way of creating these
databases or or caches, right? Um
because one of the key challenges of
long context is knowing like you know,
what things do you store or not again?
And I I think that one of the potential,
for example, use cases of things like
H-nets is um exploring their potential
for long context modeling because
uh what you can do is, you know, you you
can imagine if you can keep iterating
this, then you can basically try to
compress your your context into higher
and higher level abstractions or
memories that are like um coarse
summaries of this thing, but but then
allows like an inner model to attend
over much fewer things and in a much
kind of like uh higher-level way. So, I
think that's a really directly an
inspiration for this.
Um
I don't have like a further progress on
that particular idea, but I do think
it's it's clearly related to the whole
philosophy of why one might want to do
this.
Uh I'll read a couple questions from
online.
Um someone asked, do SSMs outperform
transformers in data-constrained
or small language model settings or vice
versa given their different inductive
biases?
Um good question. I don't know the
answer to that off the top of my head.
Um
yeah, I think for language modeling, a
lot of people care about scaling. Um
I actually don't know. I will say I
found out a little tidbit of information
yesterday, which is
um I think OpenAI recently released this
uh parameter golf challenge. I don't
know if you guys have seen it. Um but
people have been trying to train like
really small models, and I saw that
somebody was trying to train a Mamba-3
base model there, which was doing decent
well uh decently well, um but they had a
lot of kind of ablations on their um
submission, and one thing they said is
that uh even though the model works
well, at least including like a little
bit of attention was actually pretty
critical. So, uh when you have like
these really tiny models, um that's
actually something I didn't know about
before. Um
so, I don't really know the answer, but
that's as far as I know.
Uh one last one. Um with transformers,
people look at attention maps as a form
of interpretability. Is there a similar
work or proxy for SSMs given the
information compression?
I think this one is harder. So, there
actually are I don't think I have the
slides for it, but there is kind of a
correspondence between some flavors of
SSMs and um attention. So, um
I guess as I mentioned at the very
beginning, like uh there's many names
for these models, and one of the names
is linear attention. So, there's a
there's a much deeper connection between
SSMs and linear attention, and that's
implicitly related to attention. But uh
at the end of the
basically, one thing you can do is
visualize an attention-like map.
Um
it's not literally attention matrix, but
it basically you can visualize like the
dependence on every token with every
other token in a similar way to
attention.
Um and that visualization
um
I I mean, it's basically an attention
map, and you can kind of do the same
sort of comparisons.
Uh and it's actually pretty revealing of
the type of behavior that it can do. So,
for example, um that visualization, for
example, shows that
um
attention sometimes can really act like
hard attention and only, you know, pay
attention to specific tokens, while SSMs
generally always kind of like squish
everything together, and it's it can be
pretty diffuse. Um this is probably not
the only visualization that's relevant.
Um
but um yeah, I think I think a lot of
this is kind of ongoing work too to do
more mechanistic interpretability of
these models.
Okay, great. Let's give another round of
applause for our speaker, Albert.
>> [applause]
>> All right. So, now um we have um
uh some brief um
uh information from some of our
sponsors, um in particular, MongoDB.
Um but thank you all so much for being
here. I promise I'll be very quick,
about 10 minutes or so. But hi,
everyone. My name is Anaiya Raisinghani.
I'm a senior technical evangelist at
MongoDB. Um and we are so excited to be
sponsoring CS 25 this quarter.
And I'm here right now uh because
there's a genuinely interesting
engineering problem that I think is
worth about 10 minutes of your time, and
because MongoDB happens to be a really
great way of solving it.
So, you're all in this room because
you're thinking about transformers,
about multimodal models, and about what
comes next in AI, right? Here's what I
want to help add to that conversation.
The latest multimodal models have gotten
really good at understanding a document
the way a human being does.
The question now is whether your data
infrastructure is accurately keeping up.
And today I want to show you what it
looks like when the model and the
database are actually designed to work
together. So, I'm going to start off
with a concrete scenario, walk you
through why the standard approach breaks
down, and then show you what a better
architecture actually looks like
end-to-end. So, let's get into it.
So, first off, let's set the scene. Um
we're going to be talking about an
insurance company, not the sexiest
example, but a really good example. So,
let's say that your insurance company
gets about 10,000 claims a day, and each
one of these claims is a PDF, and these
claims include damage photos, tables of
repair estimates, signatures, and the
key here is that no two claims look the
same.
This is actually a real dashboard that
was built by MongoDB.
Um and what you're seeing on the left is
an active claim, which is a smashed
windshield. On the right, claims like
this, five similar claims are pulled
back instantly with loss amounts, dates,
and notes attached.
And they just recently asked, "Show me
crashes like this one," and the system
knew exactly what to return.
So, the question is, how do you build
that? And how do you build that with
retrieving back accurate information?
Because the hard part, as most of us
probably know, isn't the search. It's
what happens to those PDFs before
retrieval even starts.
And until recently, the standard
approach looked a lot like this.
You would OCR the document and extract
whatever text you could, chunk it into
pieces, pass those chunks to an
embedding model, store the vectors, and
then retrieve a query.
And this works completely fine for very
clean text documents, right? But how
many documents out there, especially
when you're dealing with insurance
claims, health care, law, how many of
those are truly perfectly clean text? Um
a lot of context can get lost even
before you start searching.
And the moment you OCR a damaged photo,
the tables in the documents, the
handwritten notes, so much important
information um that can completely alter
the whole trajectory of your claim can
be accidentally omitted. And in
situations like these, you don't want
any crucial information to be left out,
right?
So, Vision Rag makes one fundamental
change. Instead of parsing the document
into text first, you actually embed the
entire page itself as a single
multimodal vector.
So, let's chat about the new pipeline a
little bit. You have text and image
documents that come in. They go straight
to a multimodal embedding model with no
OCR step. The references and embeddings
go straight into MongoDB Atlas as your
vector store. And then at query time,
the same model is able to embed the
query and search finds the closest
pages, and a vision-capable LLM reads
the actual images to help generate your
answer.
So, what makes this work? And have any
of you in the audience um heard of
Voyage AI? I know Tengyu is a professor
here, so maybe some of you have.
No worries if not, you can look him up
after. Um so, how does this work? But to
ensure your important data isn't getting
omitted in the process,
um it all really comes down to the
embedding model.
So, with earlier multimodal multimodal
models, which were clip-based
architectures, they ran separate
encoders for text and images. So, vision
trunk on one side, text on the other,
and then they were just routed together.
The problem is that those outputs are
very independently biased. Your text
query and your image query aren't really
in the same vector space, which means
cross-modal retrieval completely
unreliable.
The Voyage multimodal 3.5 model uses a
single encoder for both. So, text and
visual inputs go in together and come
out in one unified vector space.
This is what really closes that modality
gap. So, a text query like smashed
windshield from rear impact and an image
of exactly that damage are now directly
comparable one-to-one.
It also supports interleaved text and
images. So, for a PDF page where a table
might sit next to a paragraph, um they
both get captured together, whereas
before they might get routed separately.
So, now let's kind of go back to our
insurance example using an image example
and the actual data flow. So, a claims
adjuster uploads a photo, the query
image, which is the cracked windshield.
That image goes to the embedder, which
produces a vector. Then that vector goes
into MongoDB Atlas, where it's compared
against your entire vectorized claims
collection using vector search. And what
comes back from that? The top five most
similar most visually similar claims
from your history. This means that
you're not dependent on just keyword
matches, but actual visual similarity.
And the system found these because of
the damage patterns, the angle, the type
of impact. Um all of these live inside
of the embedding.
And because MongoDB stores the vector in
the same document as everything else,
because we are a vector database,
um and it's storing that vector next to
your claim ID, the loss amount, the
adjuster notes, the repair history, you
get all of that context back in one
query, not in a separate system, but the
exact same record.
So, let's zoom out a little bit and look
at the architecture in question. On the
left side, we have what most rag stacks
look like today. You have your
operational database for your
application data and a completely
separate vector database for retrieval.
You have embedding models running in
between, um a reranker layer, so many
moving pieces. And now let's take a look
at the right side. MongoDB Atlas is a
single platform with full-text search,
vector search, embedding models,
rerankers, everything all in one. So,
this means that your multimodal data,
your vectors, are all in the same
document. And for those 10,000 insurance
claims, um your vectors actually live
right next to your claim notes and your
other source data, which means that
there's nothing that you need to sync or
glue together.
And this leaves us with a truly genuine
architectural shift, right? It changes
how you handle your unstructured data,
which was the old pipeline that started
leaving out very crucial information. Um
it starts to think about Well, you can
change how you think about the modality
gap in your retrieval. So, once again,
you have one encoder, one vector space,
and your text queries and your visual
documents are directly comparable. And
then it also changes how you design the
database layer beneath your AI
applications. So, when your operational
store and your vector store are the
exact same system, you eliminate an
entire category of infrastructure
complexity.
And just to sum it all up, when your
database thinks in documents the same
way that your models think in tokens, um
you start you stop fighting your
infrastructure and you start to get
results.
Uh for a deeper dive into Vision Rag and
also Video Rag, please check out the
article that this talk is based from by
my fantastic coworker, um Thibault
Grasdal, who's a senior technical PMM
for MongoDB. And I've linked the article
right up here.
And I'm going to quickly hand it over to
my other coworker, Patrick, who's just
going to sum up MongoDB for startups for
you all and then also talk a little bit
about the Frontier Lunch Club. But thank
you so much for having me.
>> [applause]
>> Hello.
Thank you so much, Naya. Hi, everyone. I
just wanted a quick second to introduce
myself. Um my name is Patrick Steen. I'm
on our Ventures team at MongoDB.
Uh I just want to quickly say thank you
for having us here today, uh getting to
talk with everyone, and also introduce
our MongoDB for startups program. Uh
being at Stanford gives a really high
signal that a lot of you are interested
in being future founders. I feel like on
Zoom and in this class, uh we got some
here today. Uh so, just wanted to offer
um all of you being able to sign up uh
to our startup program. This will allow
you to access Atlas credits, uh special
uh one-on-one technical expertise and
advice, as well as some go-to-market uh
opportunities. Uh we host a lot of
different events. I feel like uh being a
founder, having a great product is half
the battle, so building relationships
and uh getting to utilize that is
something we would love to help you
with. Uh so, yeah. Feel free to hit me
up on LinkedIn if you guys have any
ideas or I can help connect you at all.
And then secondly, would also I believe
you guys have seen this before, um our
Frontier Lunch Club um that we are going
to be sponsoring this year. Uh it's got
some really great opportunities
partnered with the AGI House. Um this
allows you connect into the recruiting
pipeline, um help you get a leg up on
future opportunities. You're looking to
connect with different AI researchers
and uh research institutions.
Um also, we are going to be hosting a
couple of events. One's going to be a
dinner on the 30th. Um if you'd like to
scan the QR code, it just takes 30
seconds to access that WhatsApp. And
then also in the back, Alexa is going to
be helping out um passing out um some
pizza. Um she's also a great connection
at the AGI House. Um they have a ton of
different event opportunities, as well
as connections to pretty much everyone
you would need to know to be successful
in the Bay. And then lastly, we're going
to be hosting an event later in October,
um where we're going to be kind of doing
a project competition um ran on MongoDB,
uh where you could potentially win
$1,000. So,
yeah. Just wanted to introduce myself
and uh tell you a little bit about two
things, but thank you so much for having
us. And uh
yeah. Thanks again.